Register of the Paul Robert Hanna Papers, 1920-1997
Hoover Institution Archives
- INCREMENT OF MARCH 1985
  - SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1928-1979
    - "The School and the Future of Mankind," article
      - Hawaii Educational Review, March 1952. (Folder 157: 16)
    - "The Community School Defined," address before the Philippine Normal College, Manila, April 22, 1952. (Folder 157: 17)
    - "Educating the Economic Man," address to the Third Biennial Conference of the Philippine Association of Christian Schools and Colleges,", April 1952. (Folder 157: 18)
      Printed copies (3).
    - "The School and the Future of Mankind," article, The North Dakota Teacher, April 1952. (Folder 157: 18A)
    - Address on economic development and mass education before the UNESCO Philippine Education Foundation, Manila, May 17, 1952. (Folder 157: 19)
    - "Schools and Mankind," article, New Mexico School Review, October 1952. (Folder 157: 20)
    - "Spelling - From Spoken Word to Written Symbol," article, The Elementary School Journal, February 1953. (Folder 157: 21-22)
      Printed copies (2).
    - "The School and the Future of Mankind," article, Virginia Journal of Education, February 1953. (Folder 157: 23)
      Printed copy (with annotations).
    - "The University: Instrument of Economic and Social Development," speech, Philippine Women's University, March 22, 1953. (Folder 157: 24)
    - "Spelling - From Spoken Word to Written Symbol," article, The Education Digest, May 1953. (Folder 157: 25)
    - "The Community School Defined," article, The Education Digest, September 1953. (Folder 157: 26)
    - "The Educational Program," report, Mutual Security Agency, Philippines, 1953. (Folder 157: 27)
    - "The University: Instrument of Economic and Social Development," address, Philippine Women's University, 1953. (Folder 157: 28)
    - Addresses by Paul Hanna and W. Cowley Upon the Occasion of Their Installation as Lee Jacks Professor of Child Education and David Jacks Professor of Higher Education, Stanford University, April 30, 1954. (Folder 157: 29)
      Typescript of speech, program, text of addresses.
    - "Education For Survival and Progress," address at the Jacks Professorships Installation Ceremonies, Stanford University, April 30, 1954. (Box-folder 158: 1)
      Typescript (photocopy), program, text of addresses at the ceremonies.
    - "We Teach Both Subject Matter and Children," article, NEA Journal, May 1954. (Folder 158: 2)
    - "Give Thanks Unto Our Critics," article, 1954. (Folder 158: 3)
    - "International Relations and Area Studies," chapter, Stanford Self-Study, 1954. (Folder 158: 4)
    - "Topics in the Social Sciences," research report, 1954. (Folder 158: 5)
    - "The Social Studies Program," paper, Elementary Education Conference, Austin, Texas, March 24-26, 1955. (Folder 158: 6)
    - "Hanna Survey,", May 1955. (Folder 158: 7)
    - "Social Studies for Today," article, NEA Journal, January 1956. (Folder 158: 8)
    - "The University - Instrument of National Progress," speech, Rotary of Manila, March 8, 1956. (Folder 158: 9)
    - Basic Agreement Between Leland Stanford Junior University and the United States International Cooperation Administration (ICA), March 23, 1956. (Folder 158: 10)
    - "Program for a Look to the Future," conference at W. K. Kellogg Foundation, Battle Creek, Michigan, June 21 -23, 1956. (Folder 158: 11)
    - "Education and Foreign Operations," Bulletin No. V, June 27, 1956. (Folder 158: 12)
    - "Education in the Far East," article with Sidney High, Jr., Phi Delta Kappan, June 1956. (Folder 158: 13)
    - "Philippine Educators Show the Way," article, Education, June 1956. (Folder 158: 14)
    - Brief Initial Report on the Stanford University-Philippine Department of Education-ICA Contract, July 9, 1956. (Box-folder 159: 1)
    - "A Guide to Geographic Content in the Social Studies," article, Education, September 1956. (Folder 159: 2)
    - "Educational News and Editorial Comment," The Elementary School Journal, October 1956. (Folder 159: 3)
    - First Semi-annual Report on the Philippine Department of Education-Stanford University-ICA Contract, December 1, 1956 (Folder 159: 4)
    - "Give Thanks Unto Our Critics," article, The National Elementary Principal, December 1956. (Folder 159: 5)
      Typescript (mimeographed copy) and printed copies (2).
    - Planning a Good Year for Grade 1 in Social Studies, Scott, Foresman and Company, 1956. (Folder 159: 6)
    - "Society-Child-Curriculum," article, Education 2000 AD, 1956. (Folder 159: 7)
    - "Continuing Education in a Private University," proposal to the W. K. Kellogg Foundation from Stanford University, January 1957. (Folder 159: 8)
    - Philippine Department of Education-Stanford University-ICA Contract, Second Semi-annual Report, January 1, 1957 - June 30, 1957 (Folder 159: 9)
    - "Remarks of Dr. Paul Hanna Before the 48th Annual Convention of School Students," article, The Education Quarterly, June 1957. (Folder 159: 10)
    - "Organization and Administration of the Public Schools, Territory of Hawaii,", June 30, 1957
      - "General Curriculum and Vocational Curriculum" (Folder 159: 11)
      - "The Personnel Program" (Folder 159: 12)
      - "Social Setting, Organization and Finance" (Folder 159: 13)
      - "Summary Report" (Folder 159: 14)
    - Philippine Department of Education-Stanford University-ICA Contract, Third Semi-annual Report, July 1, 1957 -December 31, 1957 (Folder 159: 15)
    - "First Grade: Your Child's Most Important Year," article, Parade, September 15, 1957. (Folder 159: 16)
    - Rea, Thelma M., "Discipline in Oral-Aural Discrimination As a Factor in Developing Power in Spelling," dissertation proposal,", October 1957. (Folder 159: 17)
    - "We Practice Conservation," interview, CTA Journal, November 1957. (Folder 159: 18)
    - Hawaiian Survey, 1957. (Folder 159: 19)
      Newspaper clippings.
    - Moore, Hollis A., Studies in School Administration, 1957. (Box-folder 160: 1)
    - "Society-Child-Curriculum," article, Education 2000 AD, Syracuse University Press, 1957. (Folder 160: 2)
    - "Remarks by Paul Hanna," speech in response to the Award of 1958, Philippine Public School Teachers Association, Philippine Educator, June 1958. (Folder 160: 3)
    - Harvard Summer School, Opportunities for Graduate Study in Elementary Education, June 30 - August 13, 1958 (Folder 160: 4)
    - Philippine Department of Education-Stanford University Contract, Fourth Semi-annual Report, July 1, 1958 (Folder 160: 5)
    - Stanford University News Service press release, Hanna proposal for a national curriculum design, September 15, 1958 (Folder 160: 6)
    - "Design for a National Curriculum," article, The Nation's Schools, September 1958. (Folder 160: 7)
      Reprint, photocopy, printed copy.
    - Excerpts from lecture on "Society-Child-Social Studies Curriculum" by Paul Hanna, 1958 Donner Summit Audio-Visual-Social Studies Workshop, October 1958. (Folder 160: 8)
    - "What Leaders Think About a 'Design for a National Curriculum,'" article, The Nation's School, November 1958. (Folder 160: 9)
    - "Design for a National Curriculum," article, The Education Digest, December 1958. (Folder 160: 10)
    - "Pioneering Investment," article, The American Tree Farmer, Winter 1958. (Folder 160: 11)
    - "The 6th Milestone - ICA and Education in the Philippines,", 1958. (Folder 160: 12)
    - Philippine Department of Education-Stanford University Contract, Fifth Semi-annual Report, January 1, 1959 (Folder 160: 13)
    - "Design for a National Curriculum," address, New Trier Township High School, February 20, 1959, program. (Folder 160: 14)
    - Notes for talk to Detroit Schools Spelling Committee, March 1959. (Folder 160: 15)
      Handwritten.
    - "Spelling as a School Subject: A Brief History," with Jean Hanna, article, The National Elementary Principal, May 1959. (Folder 160: 16)
      Printed copies (2) and reprints (2)
    - "Should the United States Have a General Curriculum Outline to Guide the Over-all Educational Program of this Nation?" paper, NEA Convention, June 29, 1959. (Folder 160: 16A)
    - Philippine Department of Education-Stanford University Contract, Terminal Reports, June 30, 1959
      - Baybay National Agricultural School, 1956-59 (Folder 160: 17)
      - Central Luzon Agricultural College, 1956-59 (Folder 160: 18)
    - Philippine Department of Education-Stanford University Contract, Sixth Semi-annual Report, July 1, 1959 (Box-folder 161: 1)
    - Fifteenth Administrative and Supervisory Work Conference, Dallas School District, August 17-28, 1959. (Folder 161: 2)
      Program.
    - Ten Dissertations Resulting from Research Project for Elementary Social Studies, Stanford University, September 1, 1959 (Folder 161: 3)
    - American Council on Education, Forty-Second Annual Meeting, "College Teaching," Washington, D.C., October 8-9, 1959 (Folder 161: 4)
      program
    - "Psychology of Spelling," with Jean Hanna, article, The Education Digest, October 1959. (Folder 161: 5)
    - Building Spelling Power, with Jean Hanna, Houghton, Mifflin Co., 1959. (Folder 161: 6)
    - Fitzgerald, James A., "What Words Should Children Study in Spelling?", 1959 (Folder 161: 7)
    - "A National Curriculum Commission?" article, NEA Journal, January 1960. (Folder 161: 8)
      Clipping and photocopy.
    - Philippine Department of Education-Stanford University Contract, Seventh Semi-annual Report, January 1, 1960 (Folder 161: 9)
    - Department of Elementary School Principals, NEA Annual Meeting, March 26-30, 1960 (Folder 161: 10)
    - "Designing Curriculum for Today's Children - Tomorrow's Citizens," speech, Department of Elementary School Principals, NEA Annual Meeting, March 30, 1960. (Folder 161: 11)
      Typescript with notes.
    - Mange, Charles V., "Relationships Between Selected Auditory Perceptual Factors and Articulation Ability," reprint, Journal of Speech and Hearing Research, March 1960 (Folder 161: 12)
    - Philippine Department of Education-Stanford University Contract, Terminal Reports, June 30, 1960
      - Industrial Arts Teacher Education (Folder 161: 13)
      - Mindanao Agricultural College (Folder 161: 14)
    - "Educating Today's Children - Tomorrow's Citizens," speech, New Jersey State Federation District Boards of Education, Annual Workshop, September 18-20, 1960. (Folder 161: 15)
      Typescript, printed copy, and program.
    - "Spelling Today," with Jean Hanna, article, The Instructor, November 1960. (Folder 161: 16)
      Clippings (2).
    - High, Sidney C, Jr., "Vocational Industrial Education in Newly Developing Nations - A Case Study of the Philippines, 1951-56," Comparative Education Series, School of Education, Stanford University, 1960. (Folder 161: 17)
    - "Resolved, That a National Curriculum Commission is Desirable," article, The Gist of the Atlantic City Meeting, Second Issue, 1960. (Folder 161: 18)
    - "World Book Encyclopedia - A Pilot Study of Suitability of World Book Encyclopedia for Use in Junior Colleges,", April 1961. (Folder 161: 19)
    - "Proposed - A National Curriculum Commission," article, Phi Delta Kappan, May 1961. (Folder 161: 20)
    - "To Professor Paul R. Hanna from the Postdoctorals in Elementary School Education, Alumni Reunion, July 23-24, 1961," Summer 1961 Conference on Elementary School Education, Stanford University (Folder 161: 21)
    - "Education: An Instrument of National Goals," 1961 Cubberley Conference at Stanford University, July 24-29, 1961 (Folder 161: 22)
    - University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee, School of Education, "The Nature of Knowledge" Conference, November 16-18, 1961
      - Program (Folder 161: 23)
      - "Structure of Knowledge: The Interrelationship of Ideas," (Folder 161: 24)
        printed copy
    - "Phonemic Analysis of 10,000 English Words for Cues to Improvement of Instruction in Spelling," project, November 27, 1961. (Box-folder 162: 1)
    - Dinner Honoring the Holders of Stanford's Endowed Fellowships, November 30, 1961 (Folder 162: 2)
    - Caswell, Hollis L., "Control of the Curriculum in American Schools," Columbia University, 1961 (Folder 162: 3)
    - "In the Americas," booklet, Scott, Foresman and Company, 1961 (Folder 162: 4)
    - Miscellany on Hanna's spelling approach, 1961 (Folder 162: 5)
    - Stanford Endowed Fellowships, 1961-62 (Folder 162: 6)
    - American Educational Research Association, Annual Meeting, February 19-21, 1962
      - "Education: An Instrument of Economic and Social Development in Newly Developing Countries." (Folder 162: 7)
      - Program (Folder 162: 8)
    - Davies, Gordon F., "Map Skills and Understandings in Intermediate School Social Studies," dissertation, Stanford University School of Education, March 1962 (Folder 162: 9)
    - "Education as an Economic and Social Instrument in the Newly Developing Nations," article, Phi Delta Kappan, May 1962. (Folder 162: 10)
      Printed copies (2), photocopy.
    - "Is the Traditional Concept of Local Control of Public Education Still Valid?" article, Journal of Secondary Education, May 1962. (Folder 162: 11)
    - World Confederation of Organizations of the Teaching Profession (WCOTP), "Impact on Education of Terrorist Activities in Vietnam,", May 18-26, 1962 (Folder 162: 12)
    - "The Tenth Milestone - A Decade of Philippine-American Cooperation in the Development of Public Education in the Philippines," report, June 30, 1962. (Folder 162: 13)
    - NEA Convention, Denver, July 1-6, 1962
      - "The NEA's Role in Curriculum and Instruction," speech. (Folder 162: 14)
      - Program and related correspondence (Folder 162: 15)
    - "America's Emerging Role in Overseas Education," conference, Syracuse University, July 11-12, 1962
      - "Conventional and Unconventional Education for Developing Nations," paper. (Folder 162: 16)
        Typescript (carbon copy) with annotations.
      - Program (Folder 162: 17)
    - "Phoneme-Grapheme Relationships Basic to Cues for Improvement," project, August 29, 1962. (Folder 162: 18)
    - "Education and Development: The Role of Educational Planning in the Economic Development of the Republic of China," report, Stanford Research Institute, October 1962. (Folder 162: 19)
    - Overseas, "News and Notes - Education in the Pacific Area,", December 1962 (Folder 162: 19A)
    - Clymer, Theodore, "Research Design in the Language Arts," reprint, Elementary English, 1962 (Folder 162: 19B)
    - "Content in the Social Studies - Generalizations From the Social Sciences," with John R. Lee, article, 1962 (Folder 162: 20)
      National Council for the Social Studies. Reprint.
    - "Conventional and Unconventional Education for Newly Developed Countries," article, America's Emerging Role in Overseas Education, 1962
      - Reprints (5) (Box-folder 163: 1)
      - Visual aids (Folder 163: 2)
    - Education - An Instrument of National Goals, P. Hanna, editor, McGraw-Hill, 1962 (Folder 163: 3)
    - "A Summary - Linguistic Cue for Spelling Improvement," Stanford University Project No. 1991, January 2, 1963 to December 31, 1964. (Folder 163: 4)
    - "Revising the Social Studies: What is Needed?", January 27, 1963. (Folder 163: 5)
    - "Curriculum and Instruction," article, NEA Journal, January 1963. (Folder 163: 6)
      Printed copy, clipping, reprints (2).
    - "Promising Trends in Education," speech, Shoreline Basic Curriculum Guide In-Service, February 11, 1963. (Folder 163: 6A)
      Typescript (mimeographed copy) and brochure.
    - "Educational Investment in the Pacific Community," conference, Stanford University, March 28-30, 1963. (Folder 163: 7)
      Report, brochures (2).
    - "Strengthening the Social Studies Program: A Critical National Need," Department of Elementary School Teachers, NEA Annual Meeting, March 30 - April 3, 1963 (Folder 163: 8)
    - "Mounting a National Effort in the Social Studies," paper, Department of Elementary School Teachers, NEA Annual Meeting, April 3, 1963. (Folder 163: 9)
    - "The University and the Government,", April 14, 1964. (Folder 163: 10)
    - "Revising the Social Studies: What is Needed?" article, Social Education, April 1963. (Folder 163: 11)
      Printed copies (2) and reprint.
    - "The Role of Higher Education in Governmental Planning for International Education," policy statement, The Commission on International Education, April 1963. (Folder 163: 12)
      Printed copies (6).
    - "Mounting a National Effort in the Social Studies," article, The National Elementary Principal, May 1963. (Folder 163: 13)
    - "Spelling and Communications Theory," article, Elementary English, May 1963. (Folder 163: 14)
    - June 23 Reception Control List, Stanford University Faculty/Staff Directory, Spring 1963 (Folder 163: 15)
    - "The Social Studies: Curriculum Proposals for the Future," 1963 Cubberley Conference, Stanford University, July 16-18, 1963 (Box-folder 164: 1)
    - San Diego County Districts, "Professional Growth Day,", September 4, 1963 (Folder 164: 2)
    - Conference on Needed Research in the Training of the Social Studies, Syracuse University, October 3-5, 1963 (Folder 164: 3)
      text of proceedings
    - International Conference for the Advancement of Educational Research, Bangkok, program, December 23-28, 1963 (Folder 164: 4)
    - Educational Strategists - Educational Planning for Developing Nations, a program at Stanford University, 1963 (Folder 164: 5)
    - Shoreline Public Schools, Basic Curriculum Guide Revision Project, Preliminary Report, 1963 (Folder 164: 6)
    - The Social Studies: Curriculum Proposals for the Future, papers presented at the 1963 Cubberley Conference, Stanford University (Folder 164: 7)
    - Strickland, Ruth G., "The Contribution of Structural Linguistics to the Teaching of Reading, Writing and Grammar in the Elementary School,", January 1964 (Folder 164: 8)
    - Higgins, John M., "Social Studies for Today's Needs," reprint, The Social Studies, February 1964 (Folder 164: 9)
    - The Use of New Educational Techniques in the Developing Countries, report of a conference, February 25-28, 1966 (Box-folder 165: 4)
    - Ford Foundation, Context the World, February 1966 (Folder 165: 5)
    - "Needed Research in Spelling," with Jean Hanna, Sidney Berquist, Richard Hodges and E. H. Rudorf, article, The Education Digest, May 1966. (Folder 165: 6)
      Printed copy, clipping.
    - "Curriculum Innovations for the State's Quality Growth As We Approach 2,000 AD," report to California State Committee on Public Education, October 31, 1966. (Folder 165: 7)
    - Horn, Thomas D., Research on Handwriting and Spelling, Natonal Council of Teachers of English, 1966 (Folder 165: 8)
    - Encyclopedia Britannica Educational Corporation, Basic Instructional Materials, 1966-67 (Folder 165: 9)
      Catalog
    - "Answering Your Questions About the 'Power to Spell' Series," with Jean Hanna, Hodges & Rudorf, Houghton Mifflin Company, January 27, 1967. (Folder 165: 10)
    - Horn, Thomas D., "Handwriting and Spelling," Review of Educational Research, April 1967 (Folder 165: 11)
    - Quillen, I. James, eulogy of, August 10, 1967. (Folder 165: 12)
    - Bezanson, Keith A., "A Tribute to Professor Paul R. Hanna," Hypothesis - Education Council Newsletter, Fall 1967 (Folder 165: 13)
    - "Roundtable Review," article, Research in the Teaching of English, Fall 1967. (Folder 165: 14)
    - "Linguistic Cues for Spelling Improvement," with Jean Hanna, Hodges and Rudorf, article, Elementary English, December 1967. (Folder 165: 15)
    - Encyclopedia Britannica Educational Corporation, Catalog of Educational Films, 1967 (Folder 165: 16)
    - Hodges, Richard E., "The Case for Teaching Sound-to-Letter Correspondences in Spelling," a report on the Stanford Spelling Project, 1967 (Folder 165: 17)
    - Horn, Ernest, What Research Says to the Teacher -Teaching Spelling, NEA, 1967 (Folder 165: 18)
    - "Power to Spell," with Jean Hanna, Hodges, Rudorf, and Berquist, Houghton Mifflin Company, 1967 (Folder 165: 19)
    - Shane, Harold G., Linguistics and the Classroom Teacher, NEA, 1967 (Box-folder 166: 1)
    - Stanford University, School of Education, "SIDEC -Stanford International Development Education Center,", 1967 (Folder 166: 2)
    - "New Directions in Elementary Social Studies," article, Weekly Reader 5 Teacher's Edition, January 31, 1968. (Folder 166: 3)
    - "Systems Analysis and Higher Education," paper, "The Role of Higher Education in National Development in Asia," seminar, Seoul, Korea, August 1968. (Folder 166: 4)
    - "Higher Education and National Development in Asia," article, The Asia Foundation Program Quarterly, September 1968. (Folder 166: 5)
    - "Implications for Education," presentation, Como Conference on Learning, Como, Italy, November 11, 1968. (Folder 166: 6)
    - "A Glossary of Linguistic Terms Helpful in the Study of Spelling," Houghton Mifflin Company, 1968 (Folder 166: 7)
    - Stanford International Development Education Center, Stanford International Studies, Graduate and Professional Programs, 1968-69 (Folder 166: 8)
    - "The Peace Corps and the University," preface by P. Hanna, April 1969. (Folder 166: 9)
    - Stanford University press release, P. Hanna as chairman of a special U.S. government committee suggesting the expansion of the Peace Corps into an International Volunteer Development Corps, May 7, 1969. (Folder 166: 10)
      Includes a clipping from The Stanford Observer, June 1969.
    - "Introducing a New Social Sciences Program -Investigating Man's World," Scott, Foresman and Company, 1969 (Folder 166: 11)
    - "The Community School and It's Administration,", September 1969 (Folder 166: 12)
    - "Elements Essential to Cooperative Educational Assitance Programs," speech, Institute of International Education Conference, October 29-31, 1969. (Folder 166: 13)
    - "Education and the Creation of Multinational Communities of Men," chapter, The United States and International Education, University of Chicago Press, 1969. (Box-folder 167: 1)
    - "Investigating Man's World Helps Children Make Their Present and Future Decisions Responsible Ones," Scott, Foresman and Company, 1969 (Folder 167: 2)
    - Schramm, Wilbur, Classroom Out-of-Doors, preface by P. Hanna, Sequoia Press/Publishers, 1969 (Folder 167: 3)
    - Association for Supervision and Curriculum Development, NEA, "A Report to the Membership,", January 1970 (Folder 167: 4)
      Building America reference
    - "Tree Farming," paper, Redwood Region Conservation Council Youth Growth Management Conference, October 16, 1970, Scott Valley, California. (Folder 167: 5)
    - "Printed Materials Will Supplement Videorecordings," article, College Management, May 1971. (Folder 167: 6)
    - "What Effect Wil the Much-touted Videorecords Have On Education?" article, School Management, July 1971. (Folder 167: 7)
    - SEAMEO/SEADAG Seminar on Non-Formal Education, Final Report, Penang, October 11-14, 1971 (Folder 167: 8)
    - "Hamline's Linkage to a Global Library System," (speech at Bush Memorial Library dedication) article, Hamline University Bulletin, November 1971. (Folder 167: 9)
    - Southeast Asian Ministers of Education Secretariat (SEAMES), Director's Annual Report, 1971 (Folder 167: 10)
    - Spelling Structure and Strategies, with Jean Hanna and Richard Hodges, Houghton Mifflin Co., 1971. (Folder 167: 11)
    - Stanford International Studies, 1971 (Box-folder 168: 1)
    - Grindings, Rotary International Club, San Francisco, January 25, 1972 (Folder 168: 2)
    - Michigan Department of Education, "Early Elementary Level Social Studies Textbooks,", January 1972 (Folder 168: 3)
    - "Multinational Community Building," paper, National Foreign Policy Conference for Leaders in Higher Education, Washington, D.C., May 1972. (Folder 168: 4)
      Printed copy, photocopy.